National Visionary Leadership Project Interviews and Conference Collection AFC 2004/007
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
- Series III: Interviews
  - James "Bud" Ward oral history interview conducted by Renee Pousssaint, 2005-11-14, AFC 2004/007: 115
    - Graphic Images, 14 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 30/436)
    - Moving Images, 4 videocassettes of 4 (DVC) (256 min.): sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 115.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 115.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 115.MV.003; AFC 2004/007: 115.MV.004
  - Walter Washington oral history interview conducted by Renee Poussaint, 2003-08-14, AFC 2004/007: 116
    Walter Washington was a lawyer and the first elected mayor of Washington, D.C.
    The interview includes Walter Washington's memories of growing up in Jamestown, New York and attending Howard University. He recalls segregation in Washington, D.C. and picketing drug stores that refused to serve African Americans. He discusses his appointment as Mayor-Commissioner by President Lyndon Johnson, Lady Bird Johnson's beautification programs and the 1968 riots in Washington, D.C.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655498
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (27 pages) (Box-folder 13/138)
    - Graphic Images, 17 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 30/437)
    - Moving Images, 3 videocassettes of 3 (Betacam SP) (90 min.): sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 116.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 116.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 116.MV.003
  - Clifton Wharton and Dolores Wharton oral history interview conducted by Renee Poussaint, 2003-03-11, AFC 2004/007: 117a
    Clifton Wharton was an economist, business executive, university president and U.S. Deputy Secretary of State. Dolores Wharton was an art historian and business executive.
    The interview includes Clifton Wharton's memories of growing up in Boston, Massachusetts, traveling around the world with his diplomat father, and attending Harvard University. He recalls joining the air force, working for the Rockefeller Foundation and becoming president of Michigan State University. With his wife Dolores, the two discuss how they met, their marriage, and moving to Chicago while Clifton attended the University of Chicago for his PhD in economics. They remember living in Asia, raising their children, the student demonstrations at Michigan State University, and Dolores' work on many corporate boards.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655555
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (126 pages) (Box-folder 13/139)
    - Graphic Images, 35 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 30/438)
    - Moving Images, 7 videocassettes of 7 (Betacam SP) (210 min.) sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 117a.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 117a.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 117b.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 117b.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 117b.MV.003; AFC 2004/007: 117b.MV.004; AFC 2004/007: 117b.MV.005
  - L. Douglas Wilder oral history interview conducted by Camille O. Cosby, 2004-09-29, AFC 2004/007: 118
    L. Douglas Wilder was a lawyer, Virginia State Senator and the first elected African American governor.
    The interview includes L. Douglas Wilder's memories of growing up in Richmond, Virginia, attending Virginia Union University and joining the navy during the Korean War. He recalls attending Howard University Law School, becoming a lawyer in Richmond and his successful run for the Virginia State Senate. He discusses campaigning for Governor of Virginia and becoming the first elected African American governor in the United States. He also discusses his accomplishments in office and founding the National Slavery Museum.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655530
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (53 pages) (Box-folder 13/140)
    - Graphic Images, 24 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 30/439)
    - Moving Images, 4 videocassettes of 4 (Betacam SP) (120 min.): sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 118.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 118.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 118.MV.003; AFC 2004/007: 118.MV.004
  - Charles V. Willie oral history interview conducted by Renee Poussaint, 2006-12-15, AFC 2004/007: 119
    Charles V. Willie was a sociologist and professor of education.
    The interview includes Charles V. Willie's memories of growing up in Dallas, Texas, attending Morehouse College and earning his Ph.D. at Syracuse University. He recalls his positions as a professor and vice president of student affairs at Syracuse, researching mental health, and becoming a professor of education at Harvard University. He discusses his support of women priests in the Episcopal Church, researching the African American family and assisting school districts with desegregation plans.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2011655223
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (130 pages) (Box-folder 13/141)
    - Graphic Images, 13 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 30/440)
    - Moving Images, 6 videocassettes of 6 (Betacam SP) (180 min.) sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 119.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 119.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 119.MV.003; AFC 2004/007: 119.MV.004; AFC 2004/007: 119.MV.005; AFC 2004/007: 119.MV.006
  - John Woodruff oral history interview conducted by Camille O. Cosby, 2006-10-05, AFC 2004/007: 120
    John Woodruff was a sociologist and won a gold medal in the 800 meter event at the 1936 Olympics in Berlin.
    The interview includes John Woodruff's memories of growing up in Pennsylvania, running track in high school and attending the University of Pittsburgh. He recalls traveling to Berlin for the 1936 Olympics and winning the 800 meter race, and later facing discrimination at races in the United States. He discusses attending New York University for a graduate degree in sociology, serving in the segregated army during World War II and Korea and his career as a social worker.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655556
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (31 pages) (Box-folder 13/142)
    - Graphic Images, 49 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 30/441)
    - Moving Images, 2 videocassettes of 2 (DVCAM) (128 min.) sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 120.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 120.MV.002
  - Samuel Yette oral history interview conducted by Renee Poussaint, 2004-07-20, AFC 2004/007: 121
    Samuel Yette was a journalist, author and teacher.
    The interview includes Samuel Yette's memories of growing up in Tennessee and attending Tennessee State University, where he founded the student newspaper. He recalls serving in the air force and attending the Indiana University Journalism School. He discusses reporting for the Afro-American, Ebony, Life Magazine and Newsweek, where he faced discrimination. He also discusses being fired from Newsweek for writing his book "The Choice" and teaching at Howard University.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655541
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (72 pages) (Box-folder 13/143)
    - Graphic Images, 24 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 30/442)
    - Moving Images, 7 videocassettes of 7 (Betacam SP) (210 min.): sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 121.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 121.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 121.MV.003; AFC 2004/007: 121.MV.004; AFC 2004/007: 121.MV.005; AFC 2004/007: 121.MV.006; AFC 2004/007: 121.MV.007
  - Andrew Young oral history interview conducted by Renee Poussaint, 1998-06-21, AFC 2004/007: 122
    Andrew Young was a minister, civil rights activist, United Nations Ambassador, the mayor of Atlanta and U.S. Representative from Georgia.
    The interview includes Andrew Young's memories of growing up in New Orleans, Louisiana and attending Howard University. He discusses his religious conversion, his involvement in the civil rights movement and working for Martin Luther King, Jr. He also recalls visiting Africa as the United Nations Ambassador and his memories of Dorothy Height.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655478
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (27 pages) (Box-folder 13/144)
    - Graphic Images, 1 photograph: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 30/443)
    - Moving Images, 3 videocassettes of 3 (Betacam SP) (90 min.): sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 122.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 122.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 122.MV.003
  - Clara Adams oral history interview conducted by Leah Taylor, 2006-11-16, AFC 2004/007: 123
    Clara Adams was a chemistry professor and administrator at Morgan State University.
    The interview includes Clara Adams' memories of growing up in Baltimore, Maryland, attending Morgan State University and Iowa State University, where she held a fellowship at the Ames Laboratory. She recalls facing discrimination in Iowa and the civil rights movement. She remembers her career as a research chemist, becoming the first female faculty member in the chemistry department at Morgan State University and the changes at the university while she was vice president of academic affairs.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655559
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (51 pages) (Box-folder 13/145)
    - Graphic Images, 1 photograph: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 31/444)
    - Moving Images, 1 videocassette of 1 (Mini DV) (60 min.): sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 123.MV.001
  - Sarah Lee Anderson oral history interview conducted by Gregory David Jackson, 2004, AFC 2004/007: 124
    Sarah Lee Anderson was a teacher and minister.
    The interview includes Sarah Lee Anderson's memories of growing up in Georgia, attending Clark College and working as a domestic when her children were young. She recalls going back to school, becoming a special education teacher and being the president of her local PTA. She also discusses her faith, teaching Sunday school, attending Bible College in North Carolina and becoming an ordained minister.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655560
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (36 pages) (Box-folder 13/146)
    - Moving Images, 2 videocassettes of 2 (MiniDV) (120 min.) sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 124.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 124.MV.002
  - Amiri Baraka oral history interview conducted by Shannon Evans, 2005-10-17, AFC 2004/007: 125
    Amiri Baraka was a poet, playwright, essayist and political activist.
    The interview includes Amiri Baraka's memories of growing up in Newark, New Jersey, attending Howard University and serving in the air force, where he was discharged and accused of being a communist. He recalls moving to New York, writing poetry with the Beat Poets and visiting Cuba. He also discusses his involvement in the civil rights and Black nationalist movements and the Million Man March.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655562
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (53 pages) (Box-folder 13/147)
    - Moving Images, 2 videocassettes of 2 (MiniDV) (120 min.) sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 125.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 125.MV.002
  - Rudolph Belisle oral history interview conducted by Byron R. Williams, 2002-10-17, AFC 2004/007: 126
    Rudolph Belisle was an entrepreneur, community activist, and warden of Orleans Parish Prison.
    The interview includes Rudolph Belisle's memories of growing up in New Orleans, attending Alabama A & M University and his first jobs. He recalls his involvement in local politics and reforming Orleans Parish Prison, where he was a warden. He discusses opening his bar and nightclub, jazz performances in New Orleans, and how integration ultimately hurt African American-owned businesses.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655563
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (99 pages) (Box-folder 14/148)
    - Graphic Images, 3 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 31/445)
    - Moving Images, 4 videocassettes of 4 (MiniDV) (240 min.): sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 126.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 126.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 126.MV.003; AFC 2004/007: 126.MV.004
  - Keter Betts oral history interview conducted by Oliver Albertini, 2002, AFC 2004/007: 127
    William "Keter" Betts was a jazz bassist, composer and music teacher.
    The interview includes Keter Betts' memories of playing bass for Dinah Washington and Ella Fitzgerald and teaching and performing in Washington, D.C. He discusses his opinions on jazz, writing music and playing drums as a child.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655564
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (21 pages) (Box-folder 14/149)
    - Graphic Images, 2 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 31/446)
    - Moving Images, 1 videocassette of 1 (MiniDV) (60 min.) sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 127.MV.001
  - Adolpho Birch oral history interview conducted by Akeia Morris, 2002-10-20, AFC 2004/007: 128
    Adolpho Birch was a lawyer and the Chief Justice of the Tennessee Supreme Court.
    The interview includes Adolpho Birch's memories of growing up in Washington, D.C. and attending Lincoln University and Howard University Law School. He recalls joining the navy, opening his own law practice in Nashville, Tennessee and representing civil rights protesters. He discusses becoming a district attorney, teaching law at several universities in Nashville and serving as the Chief Justice of the Supreme Court in Tennessee.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655565
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (33 pages) (Box-folder 14/150)
    - Graphic Images, 1 photograph: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 31/447)
    - Moving Images, 2 videocassettes of 2 (MiniDV) (120 min.): sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 128.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 128.MV.002
  - Van S. Bird oral history interview conducted by Donald Cook, 2005, AFC 2004/007: 129
    Van S. Bird was an Episcopal priest and professor of sociology.
    The interview includes Van S. Bird's memories of attending seminary at Northwestern University, marrying his wife and founding a parish in Baltimore, Maryland. He recalls earning his PhD in sociology at Temple University and teaching at LaSalle University. He also discusses studying at the Canterbury Cathedral in England and starting a church in the Virgin Islands.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655566
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (33 pages) (Box-folder 14/151)
    - Moving Images, 1 videocassette of 1 (MiniDV) (60 min.) sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 129.MV.001
  - Lillie Virginia Drake Bowman oral history interview conducted by Ernest Gibson, 2004-11-15, AFC 2004/007: 130
    Lillie Bowman was a teacher and guidance counselor in Nashville public schools.
    The interview includes Lillie Bowman's memories of growing up in Nashville and attending Tennessee State University and the University of Chicago. She recalls the integration of public schools, preparing African American students for college and becoming a guidance counselor. She also discusses her faith and offers advice to young African Americans.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655520
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (38 pages) (Box-folder 14/152)
    - Graphic Images, 2 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 31/448)
    - Moving Images, 1 videocassette of 1 (MiniDV) (60 min.): sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 130.MV.001
  - Pecolia Boyles oral history interview conducted by Candice Goodwin, 2004, AFC 2004/007: 131
    Pecolia Boyles was a caregiver in Milwaukee, Wisconsin.
    The interview includes Pecolia Boyles' memories of growing up in Mississippi, segregation and the Great Depression. She recalls moving to Milwaukee, Wisconsin, the civil rights movement and witnessing riots. She discusses her work caring for the elderly and for children.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655521
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (26 pages) (Box-folder 14/153)
    - Moving Images, 2 videocassettes of 2 (MiniDV) (120 min.): sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 131.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 131.MV.002
  - J. Robert Bradley oral history interview conducted by T. Ebony Turain, 2002-11-11, AFC 2004/007: 132
    J. Robert Bradley was a gospel and opera singer.
    The interview includes J. Robert Bradley's memories of growing up in Memphis, Tennessee, attending the Baptist Church and singing in the choir. He recalls his voice teacher, Thomas Shelby, learning to sing in many different languages and to perform opera. He discusses his faith, performing around the world and becoming the director of music for the National Baptist Convention.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655557
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (33 pages) (Box-folder 14/154)
    - Graphic Images, 1 photograph: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 31/449)
    - Moving Images, 2 videocassettes of 2 (Mini DV) (120 min.) sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; 2 videocassettes of 2 (Mini DV) (120 min.) sound, color; 1/4 in. edited master; AFC 2004/007: 132.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 132.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 132b.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 132b.MV.002
  - William Brantley oral history interview conducted by Danielle Spanner, 2004, AFC 2004/007: 133
    William Brantley was a principal and assistant superintendent.
    The interview includes William Brantley's memories of growing up in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania and becoming a principal and assistant superintendent of West Chester, Pennsylvania schools. He recalls school desegregation, the civil rights movement and raising his children. He also discusses his opinions on education and the No Child Left Behind Act.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655569
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (23 pages) (Box-folder 14/155)
    - Moving Images, 2 videocassettes of 2 (Mini DV) (120 min.) sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 133.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 133.MV.002
  - Jerome Brooks oral history interview conducted by Ileana Simien, 2002, AFC 2004/007: 134
    Jerome Brooks was a postal superintendent, businessman and real estate agent.
    The interview includes Jerome Brooks' memories of growing up in Port Arthur, Texas, facing discrimination in his first jobs and attending Prairie View A & M University. He recalls moving to Detroit, Michigan, working in auto plants and moving to Memphis, Tennessee, where he started a business. He discusses moving back to Port Arthur where he worked as a superintendent of the post office, started a real estate and construction business, and integrated the local Boy Scouts as a scoutmaster.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655570
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (97 pages) (Box-folder 14/156)
    - Graphic Images, 2 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 31/450)
    - Moving Images, 6 videocassettes of 6 (MiniDV) (360 min.) sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 134.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 134.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 134.MV.003; AFC 2004/007: 134.MV.004; AFC 2004/007: 134.MV.005; AFC 2004/007: 134.MV.006
  - Eleanor DeLoache Brown oral history interview conducted by Jessica Smith, 2005-10-21, AFC 2004/007: 135
    Eleanor DeLoache Brown was a teacher, guidance counselor, civic leader and president of Jack and Jill of America, Inc.
    The interview includes Eleanor DeLoache Brown's memories of growing up in Texas and attending Prairie View A & M University, where she majored in home economics. She recalls teaching at several universities before marrying and having children, and returning to school for elementary school teacher certification in Ohio. She discusses her career as a guidance counselor, her teaching methods, and volunteer work with Jack and Jill of America, Inc. and the League of Women Voters.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655572
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (41 pages) (Box-folder 14/157)
    - Moving Images, 2 videocassettes of 2 (MiniDV) (120 min.) sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 135.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 135.MV.002
  - Arthur Burnett oral history interview conducted by Rosa Combs, 2006-10-16, AFC 2004/007: 136
    Arthur Burnett was an Assistant U.S. Attorney and Superior Court Judge.
    The interview includes Arthur Burnett's memories of growing up in Virginia and attending Howard University. He recalls his rejection from the University of Virginia Law School because of his race, and his decision to attend New York University Law School. He discusses his army service and his career as a prosecutor at the U.S. Department of Justice, and as an Assistant U.S. Attorney and Superior Court Judge of the District of Columbia.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655574
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (42 pages) (Box-folder 14/158)
    - Moving Images, 1 videocassette of 1 (MiniDV) (60 min.) sound, color; 1/2 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 136.MV.001
  - Calvin W. Burnett oral history interview conducted by Dareise Jones, 2004-11-20, AFC 2004/007: 137
    Calvin Burnett was a psychologist and president of Coppin State University.
    The interview includes Calvin Burnett's memories of growing up in Davenport, Iowa and serving in the army. He recalls attending St. Louis University where he played basketball and earned his Ph.D. in psychology. He discusses his heroes, his family and his accomplishments as president of Coppin State University.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655575
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (56 pages) (Box-folder 14/159)
    - Moving Images, 2 videocassettes of 2 (MiniDV) (120 min.): sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 137.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 137.MV.002
  - Margaret Burroughs oral history interview conducted by Nubia Henderson, 2003-10-04, AFC 2004/007: 138
    Margaret Burroughs was an artist, poet, teacher and museum curator.
    The interview includes Margaret Burroughs' memories of growing up in Louisiana and Chicago, Illinois and attending Illinois Normal College. She recalls her career as an art teacher, her rejection of white beauty standards, and living in Mexico on a sabbatical. She discusses founding the South Side Community Art Center and DuSable Museum of African-American History, the FBI investigation of her political activities, writing poetry, and her friendship with Gwendolyn Brooks.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655576
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (56 pages) (Box-folder 14/160)
    - Moving Images, 2 videocassettes of 2 (MiniDV) (120 min.) sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 138.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 138.MV.002
  - Vada Butcher oral history interview conducted by Victoria Kirby, 2006-10-11, AFC 2004/007: 139
    Vada E. Butcher was a professor of African American music.
    The interview includes Vada Butcher's memories of growing up in St. Louis, Missouri, learning to play the piano and attending Fisk University and Chicago Music College. She discusses studying music in Europe, her career as a professor of ethnomusicology and African American spirituals, and teaching at Howard University. She also recalls the civil rights movement and segregation in Washington, D.C.
    Catalog Record: http://lccn.loc.gov/2010655577
    - Manuscripts, 1 transcript (102 pages) (Box-folder 14/161)
    - Graphic Images, 6 photographs: digital, jpeg files, color (Box-folder 31/451)
    - Moving Images, 3 videocassettes of 3 (MiniDV) (180 min.): sound, color; 1/4 in. camera master; AFC 2004/007: 139.MV.001; AFC 2004/007: 139.MV.002; AFC 2004/007: 139.MV.003
  - Earl Caldwell oral history interview conducted by Tiffany Shepard, 2006-06-26, AFC 2004/007: 140
    Earl Caldwell covered the civil rights movement as a journalist for several newspapers including the New York Times. He later became a professor of journalism.